software engineering radio episode 61
and tons of GCC
[Music]
hi everybody welcome to another episode
of software engineering radio today this
is our new interviewing Morgan Peters on
compilers and the internals of compilers
exemplified on the gnu compiler
collection Morgan would you like to say
some words about yourself
sure hello my name is Morgan deters I'm
at the Washington University in st.
Louis and st. Louis Missouri in the USA
I study under dr. Ron Citroen who is the
I suppose main compilers guy there with
many decades of research I am a PhD
student I have been there for a number
of years and I'm graduating sometime
soon in the next six months or year so
hopefully I can find a job you can maybe
I have a number I have quite a bit of
experience with static analysis with
compilers with language implementations
going back for a number of years I've
done quite a bit of work on both with
Java but also especially on java virtual
machines various kinds of static
analysis on java programs on other kinds
of programs mic analysis profiling tools
for java and various other things but
that's that's really mainly my my forte
I'm in the real time and embedded
systems group at Washington University
so most of my work ends up dealing not
just with languages programming
languages compilers but also
specifically with real time and embedded
systems various interesting boards that
we get for avionics purposes yeah great
so let's start by taking a look at why
should anyone be interested in what
compilers are and how they work what
makes that interesting and relevant for
everyday life well it makes it very
interesting and relevant because it
ultimately when you compile your
software when you write and compile your
software you want it to run efficiently
you want it to run well on modern
processors taking advantage of of what
modern hardware has to offer you and and
really that's the compilers job to
to perform ultimately that's something
you don't have to worry about too much
the the too many of the internal details
of the good new compiler collection GCC
or other compilers but fundamentally
that's that's the job of people like me
other compiler developers to to make
sure that those things that efficient
implementations of your software
programs are ultimately created okay so
this is sort of a behind-the-scenes look
at the internals of things you use
everyday it's like going to a car garage
and ask mechanics how the internals of
motor work you shouldn't really have to
worry about it but then it's interesting
and might be helpful anyway and it's
something that's very relevant
absolutely and you want to make sure
that that the compiler you're using is
something that is that is current and
and and will give you what you want on
modern hardware absolutely yeah great so
well
maybe you'd like to start by explaining
how compiler works at the top level
what's the basic idea of the workings
inner workings of a compiler so
fundamentally a compiler has to read a
plain text generally source file and
understand what that means whether it be
in C or C++ or Java and try to
understand exactly what you mean by by
writing that that text source file so
anytime you use a variable it has to
figure out which variable you're
referencing how to access that variable
if it's a local variable or a global
variable or any other kind of thing or
whether it's a type and it has to
understand the the semantic content of
of your source program in the context of
various other parts of your program that
might be included in other source files
once it figures that out it has to
generally compilers will produce some
sort of internal representation to mull
over this information to understand it
better themselves to transform it in
various ways and ultimately it has to
produce object code for the target
platform of your choice whether that is
Java bytecode if it's producing a
portable class file Java class files for
instance or whether it's producing
pentium assembly or whether it's
producing PowerPC assembly or spark or
any number of different things it has to
generate something there the
is equivalent to your original source
program but hopefully efficient because
many different translations are possible
okay so let's drill in a little more and
be specific about the gnu compiler
collection it's basically a collection
of compiler framework well that's what
you said in yesterday's tutorial so
what's special about this what sets it
apart from other compilers well the GCC
the good new compiler collection is very
heavily used it's it's very flexible
it's very portable you can run it on
many different UNIX platforms you can
run it on Windows you can run it on Mac
OS you can run it anywhere basically and
and the the key advantages are that it
accepts many different source file
inputs that can compile C and C++ and
Java and ADA and Fortran and and it can
produce output object code for many
different target architectures for
PowerPC and SPARC and arm and various
embedded systems and pentium of course
and and and so the the key advantages of
GCC are that it is so flexible and so
portable that you can pretty much rely
on it and dependent on it on it anywhere
for any kind of development in these
languages that you're producing and
except that it and rely on it to produce
object code that is effective in many
different for many different hardware
architectures how does it achieve this
flexibility sounds like it's modular in
some ways yes GCC internally is very
modular so that so fundamentally GCC is
is composed of a a language specific
front end a neutral middle end and
that's what they actually call it the
middle end that is that's a funny name
yes it actually is but but but there's
also a back end so they have to have
something so they have to have something
in the middle so they had they have a
language dependent front end which can
be swapped in either for C or C++ or
Java a a middle end which then takes the
output of this front end which is a
language independent intermediate
representation the middle end then then
manipulates and massages this this
intermediate representation
into something that's more efficient or
at least that it hopes is more efficient
either in space or in runtime and then
the output of the middle end is a
representation that the back end can use
in the back end produces specific
architecture code so the back end is
then language neutral but architecture
specific the front end is language
dependent but architecture independent
and the middle end can operate on
anything so you have any front-end in
and it's modular with the middle end and
the middle end can then work with any
back-end which is then specific only to
the architecture it's producing code for
when your architecture you means a
target platform basically a processor
and a operating system that's that's
more or less correct so a specific
instruction set that's common on not
just one chip but a family of chips so
for example the entire Intel 32 bit line
of chips for example would be one
architecture right mm-hmm okay let's
take a closer look at these three ends
of the compiler starting to the front
end I find it quite fascinating that so
different languages can be parsed and
then transform into a common abstraction
how is that possible and what does this
common abstraction look like okay so
commonly in compilers when the when the
source file this text file is initially
read it is parsed into a tree like
representation an abstract syntax tree
of some form that that contains the
representation of what is meant by the
source program so it's particularly
useful to think of it as a tree because
expressions naturally fall into a tree
our arithmetic expressions for example X
plus y the quantity times some constant
can be naturally represented by a tree
like structure well in what way well by
by having a parent node represent say an
operation like multiplication and then
it's operands it's two operands in this
case being the specific targets of that
multiplication the first operand in the
second operand that you're multiplying
by for instance in in an arithmetic
sense so once this this
this tree representation is built up
from the the source file the front-end
needs to do additional processing to
figure out exactly what is meant by that
the semantic processing phase we'll go
through and make sure that the types are
all valid that all of the variables who
reference have in fact been declared and
that they're of the correct type and
that you're not doing anything that that
would cause an error in the source
language so anything that's it's illegal
or invalid and see or create some sort
of ambiguity can be ruled out at that
point and an error can be or a warning
can be can be issued and at the same
time it goes through and completes the
tree it figures out exactly what you're
trying to mean by by different source
code constructs so and see if you're
calling a function it tries to figure
out if if that function exists and link
it up to to its representation
internally of what that function is so
that it can in later phases produce the
code actually omit that function call so
that is the sort of the validity check
based on this common abstraction that is
the output of the front ends that that
is correct this intermediate
representation which is language neutral
is then output from the front ends so C
or C++ or Java no matter what you put in
ultimately is it produces this this GCC
specific intermediate representation
this data structure tree that that is
internal in GCC that that represents
what you what you have tried to do with
with your program that something that is
then valid the it's it's valid according
to the front end so you haven't violated
any of the languages rules and and it's
something then the the later passes of
the compiler and going over this
intermediate representation can use to
to translate that program to to the
specific target of your choice so in
fact many translations internally in the
compiler are happening when you when you
look at the compiler from the outside
it's taking a source program and
producing you know pentium code that you
can then run natively on your on your
hardware but in fact internally it's
producing many different intermediate
representations and going over in many
different ways in a way that's
convenient for it like many programs
that do data processing do as well they
the internally structure it in some way
that's convenient for them and then
output some summary or translation of
that data
but getting back to this comment
restructure I mean for expressions it's
sort of straightforward how they are
represented as as a tree and I mean
expressions are present in basically any
language so that is understandable but
then there are constructs like classes
or whatever that are specific for some
of the languages and others like sieve
just don't have these how are these
represented in this common language
neutral representation well there
they're put into it so only say you have
a tree type that represents a a class or
a struct in C or C++ some sort of data
structure a composite type to be more
specific and and then that that that
tree that that represents that that
particular class or that it read in from
the from the source file then has a list
of different fields that are in that
with all of their names and access modes
and types and everything else of that
class it has a list of all of the
methods of that class anything else
that's associated to that class as part
of that tree representation the tree is
basically just a common data structure
inside of GCC front ends and that the
front end communicates with the the
middle end using it's basically just a
common way for those things to
communicate and anything that doesn't as
naturally fit into that tree structure
anything that's not an expression is
sort of forced into it but it still
works very well in the sense that these
trees are then linked and you've got a
common tree structure for absolutely
everything internally this sounds like
some sort of podium orphism with some of
the concrete types some of the concrete
node types present in the common part
and then specific extensions for the
different front ends that's true so the
the tree structure in many compilers
that are written using object-oriented
languages such as Java or C++ if you
look at the compiler source code written
in those languages you'll typically find
a an abstract base class tree node or
something of this sort that then has
different subclasses for every kind of
different tree there is so you'd have
one for an arithmetic expression and
then further subclasses of that for
addition and subtraction and so forth
and a separate
class four function types and for method
types and for data structure types and
so forth in GCC the front ends are
actually written in C and you don't have
the object-oriented support of the
language that it's written in you don't
have the the support in C to do that
sort of thing so it makes it difficult
to use pretty morphism that's true so
what they do is sort of the C equivalent
and they create they they create a and
then this is used in many different
projects not not just GCC so you can't
pick on GCC just specifically but you do
see this elsewhere this is basically pre
object objects right it's it's what it's
what you do for objects and inheritance
when you don't have that support in the
in the tart and the language you're
writing it in and that is to create a
Union to get around the type system and
to put basically anything you want
inside of that Union so different fields
of the Union are in fact all on the same
a legate in the same place in memory and
you can have a a tree note Union that
contains a field for each type of
different tree node you have and then
access them all through that that common
data structure type even though there
are actually many different types so
it's it's not something that's type safe
and it's something that is that is
unsafe and if you do something unsafe in
the GCC code then it can crash at
runtime they do have various mechanisms
for making that a little bit more
convenient than it sounds but ultimately
yes you're trying to get around not
having language support in order to do
that the reason the GCC has done this is
because they want to be very portable
they want you to be able to take an
architecture that has only a minimal C
compiler available and to be able to
create GCC from that and as part of that
of course then you get the GNU C
compiler and also the C++ compiler and
also the Java compiler and and various
other things that that are then
convenient for you and in development so
ultimately they wanted to be very
portable and they didn't want to require
you to have a C++ compiler in order to
get GCC so the idea is that GCC itself
can be bootstrapped using just a minimal
set of features sort of the standard C
features and based on that once you have
a C compiler for a platform you get the
whole GC
see rich musical features that's correct
but that also means that internally in
GCC things have to be implemented in
this this well some of it is is created
in this minimal C set and and some of it
is created assuming that it already has
GCC and if you are trying to build it
using a minimal C compiler it actually
builds a subset of itself and then
creates the rest it compiles the rest of
it using that that subset of itself so
there are parts of GCC that the main
compiler code that that are written
using this very minimal minimal
assumptions about the C compiler and
other parts of it that assume that you
have the extensions that are available
in ingénue see the the entire GCC source
base if you if you download and look at
the entire source tree you in fact find
quite a bit of C++ and Java but these
are not in the main compiler portions
these are in the standard libraries for
C++ and Java you also find a
considerable amount of ADA code if you
download the entire package and and
various other things as well
for the ADA compiler and so forth but
yeah the the front ends generally
speaking for the most part are written
entirely in C and so they don't have
objects and inheritance and things that
we've come to be and come to rely on
okay so that's now assume that we have
this common language independent
abstraction of the tree nodes as the
output of the front-end so what happens
next so the the middle end then takes
this this output from the front end this
standard language neutral tree
representation that is called Gimple
because it's it's it's called Gimple
because it's it's actually a a new c
version of the simple language from
McGill University and and it's a it's a
slightly simplified version of the tree
representation that some of the front
ends use and it doesn't have any
language extensions and at this point it
is a a standard way for the front ends
to talk to the middle end and this tree
structure is manipulated by different
middle end passes so there's a pass
manager that that accumulates many
dozens of passes that before we get to
these different passes you just
that the different front ends have nodes
that are specific to a front and now you
said it's only the standard parts of how
that transformed okay let me let me
clarify so the the front ends when they
initially parse the source file
representation and they create this tree
representation can rely on language
specific kinds of trees so for example
language features if you look at C or
C++ or Java code they have tremendous
similarities and a common representation
can do them very very well it can it can
operate very effectively on those they
all have the idea of a statement and
they all have the idea of an expression
and various arithmetic expressions and
integer types and composite types and so
forth but they do also have differences
and so the synchronized construct for
example in Java doesn't really have an
equivalent at the language level in C or
C++ and the C++ notion of a try-catch
block is different than the Java notion
of a try-catch block and so forth so
some of these features can have in in
the front end just for convenience and
writing the front end and they can have
specific tree node types that represent
exactly what they're supposed to do but
the front ends are required to resolve
all of these language specific
extensions in the tree representation
before the tree representation is passed
on to the middle end so there are
language specific extensions that are
possible just for convenience in the
front end but at some point they do have
to be translated into this this simpler
tree representation for the middle end
which is language neutral to algorithms
so it's sort of a to pass front and
first they are allowed to use extensions
for as the path tree and then in the
second pass they sort of resolve these
extensions to the common set of tree
nodes in fact the front end can perform
as many passes as it likes and many of
them do typically they they load in the
source file in some incomplete tree
format that that that doesn't doesn't
have a a full I mean it has a
representation of the source file but it
doesn't it isn't all linked up to two
other parts of it and then it typically
goes through at least one more pass to
complete this tree to do type checking
to check that you've initialized all of
your variables etc
and some of the front ends can go
through multiple passes to do this and
then yes and then at the end of the at
the end of the front end when the front
end is finally finished with all of its
operation it's in its stamping this tree
representation is being final then yes
it does have to resolve any any language
specific parts of that of that
representation okay so the front end is
basically a black box that takes text
input and gives out a tree of the
standard kind of tree nodes that's
correct so now it goes into the middle
end with these different passes of
optimizations and that's correct so the
middle ends job is to take the street
representation and produce an equivalent
tree representation which is somewhat
architecture-specific so at this point
some some architecture details come into
play such as what types of registers are
available or what types of vector
instructions are available on the on the
hardware platform but the beginning part
of the middle end doesn't really worry
about that so the middle end really
proceeds in many phases and passes as
well so the middle ends job mainly is to
produce an equivalence but slightly
lower level representation of this this
tree representation it gets from the
front end that should be more efficient
either more efficient in space smaller
code or representing what will
eventually be smaller object code or
something that is more efficient in its
memory addressing or something that is
that has fewer instructions and will
probably execute faster or something
with fewer loops or etc I mean they're
numbered number different optimizations
available and it performs many dozens of
passes to go over this tree
representation and modify it in salt
subtle ways sometimes and sometimes
totally reorganize it into something
that is equivalent from a programmatic
point of view so if you run it it should
do exactly the same thing if you were to
interpret it and execute it like a
program and and yet something that
should run faster and once also so as a
simple example some statements in your
program may never be reached some some
comparisons that you perform against
zero save sometimes perhaps the compiler
can prove to itself that
that expression can never be 0 and so if
you compare it against zero then either
your your your if test is is dead so to
speak and that's that's the terminology
used in in the compiler community and if
you're if if such a statement is or
control flow constructs is considered to
be dead then it can be removed from the
program entirely and in the case of a
conditional like an if-then it can
potentially remove a large block of code
that is dependent on that F to whatever
would never be actually run so that sort
of optimization can be performed to
change your code considerably this sort
of thing can come up actually quite
commonly when you define constants in
your program or when something happens
in your to be configurable right when
you're writing ree-ree targetable
reconfigurable software you typically
try not to hard code as many things as
possible and you define a lot of
constants you define a number of things
that then configure that software and
many times the compiler can go through
and optimize that based on the specific
configuration that it is compiling at
hand so basically this middle aims looks
at the tree representation of a single
file and does local optimizations of
that by transforming one tree
representation is another or basically
modifying the tree representation that
is correct so the middle end proceeds
through many dozen passes as I as I
mentioned through the street
representation and creates a an
equivalent tree representation for each
method in your source program or each
method or function depending on whatever
source language you're coming from so
each one has a tree that represents the
code of that function or method and
those are all optimized through these
successive passes the the high level
tree representation is translated then
into a low level representation of
statements and this is common in in many
compilers to have multiple levels of
intermediate representation and this is
also a fairly similar one that you see
in other compilers which is the register
transfer language or RTL format RTL is
basically just then a sequence of
statements that are not quite assembly
statements but that look a lot like them
they're very low-level statements set
this particular
kind of register if there's a register
of register 65 let's say so at this
level it is not quite defined yet how
many it is the compiler does not worry
about how many registers are available
in the target instruction set and it
assumes it has as many as it likes and
it calls these pseudo registers right so
you might only have a few registers like
the Pentium does but that are actually
available and symbolically expressible
in the in the target code but this level
of the compiler assumes it has as many
as a can and later it will figure that
out so it precedes RTL contains just
very simple instructions that are not a
tree-like format but just a linear
sequence of code that represents all
these different that is equivalent to
your original source program but is very
low level contains go twos and various
other things that maybe you don't have
in your original source program so it's
sort of like assembler Bob sort of
architecture independent assembler code
it's largely architecture independent
the the specific back-end that you
choose for your compiler does when you
produce your compiler the back-end that
you that you have selected does have
some say as far as what RTL instructions
are available and used so this expansion
from the tree format that I mentioned
before this high-level tree
representation into this RTL that's very
low-level is guided somewhat by which
target platform you use so if you use a
target platform with vector instructions
then the RTL is going to represent that
and anytime you do a lot of array
manipulations in a loop it might
translate that into a vector instruction
to be more efficient at when when it
actually produces the code so because
the back end is so involved in
translating this RTL ultimately to the
assembly language because of that it
also has some say and in what this RTL
looks like mm-hmm
okay so now we have this RTL and on this
RTL probing some more optimizations are
done that's correct so many passes are
then run on this RTL once the RTL is
expanded from the tree representation
various low level optimizations can then
be performed on that so these low level
optimizations include many of the same
things the same sort of dead code
elimination that I mentioned before but
the high-level details of the code are
now no longer available right you're
looking at a very low level
representation of the code there are a
lot of people optimizations that can be
made which basically if you consider it
if you think of printing out a large
page of code a very low level code maybe
assembly code or something at that level
and taking a small a small frame a slide
or a magnifying glass sort of down the
length of the code and looking for
specific sequences of instructions that
you know can be replaced with more
efficient instructions and then
replacing them that's what a people
optimization is so you're just looking
at a small range of instructions and
replacing known anti-patterns basically
with with equivalent code which you know
that to run a lot faster so this can
change addressing modes various other
things so that sort of thing is easily
performed on the RTL as well as more
global optimizations that that do look
at what is available in the low-level
representation and replace it some
things are more easily done at the low
level some things are more easily done
at the high level and and that sort of
depends you know however you want to
write your optimization pass the history
of GCC is also that in the past the tree
representation didn't exist as a
standard language neutral intermediate
representation way back in in the
wilderness stage well not the wilderness
days of GCC but but back when back when
we all knew - back when we all
originally grew to love it it didn't
have as as standard a a tree
representation so many of these tree
passes are actually pretty recent in the
compiler and originally the RTL passes
were what you had as the optimization
passes and so the front end would
produce RTL or something that could be
easily produced into translated into our
tail and then the RTL optimization
passes where all you had so historically
there are a lot of RTL low-level
optimization passes for that reason as
well and the tree ones are much newer
right now in GCC they both exist and
they probably will both continue to
exist because some optimizations are
more easily targeted at different levels
of abstraction in the code at some point
then during the RTL passes halfway
through or a little bit more than
halfway through the one RTL pass which
is probably the most important marker of
all of them is the register allocation
phase and this is where these pseudo
registers that I've said in the past
that the B compiler can
assume it has an infinite number of
registers basically and at this point it
actually has to come to terms with
reality that on the that on SPARC
architecture it has certain types of
registers and and access modes and
instructions for accessing them
efficiently and on PowerPC the story is
a little different on pentium the story
is quite different and and so it has to
actually meet reality and assign hard
registers the actual registers to
optimizations were easier to do while
you're well assuming you had as many
registers as you chose to have and then
when you're finished with the
optimizations you sort of try to break
them down and make compromises and
actually put things into memory into
immediately instead of having the
register that sort of thing that's true
that's true so many times for example
you might be using or the internal
representation of your program might be
using pseudo register 13 and pseudo
register 65 in such ways that they don't
actually overlap and at the register
allocation phase it can map those on to
the same hardware register can use the
Pentium register EAX let's say for both
of them and it has no difficulty doing
that but at some point in the in the
passes it has to discover that it can do
that sort of thing so it doesn't
necessarily cost you anything
typically what does happen is that
you're using many different values at
once and that it has to spill especially
on Pentium it has to spill many values
to the stack right so it does actually
have to go out to memory to write back
in and perform additional computations
with them so that's that's definitely
the case and during register allocation
it does as well as it can to store
frequently used variables or the
equivalence of variables at this level
of abstraction many of your program
variables in actual hardware registers
for speed but at some point yes it does
have to compromise and and accept that
some of those are going to go to memory
and then I have to be loaded back at
some point just to get some idea how
many registers do the different
architectures actually have currently oh
well I'm not I'm not the best person
maybe to to compare architectures
I'm most familiar with with x86
architectures and in the actual hardware
I think many more registers are
available the ones that were actually
that are actually usable for generic
program data on 32-bit Intel are in just
a few I mean there's the that the common
ones are EA xba EBX I'm sorry EAX EBX
ECX and EDX which of the extended ones
from way back in the in the old 16-bit
days so those are the extended you know
32-bit general registers for anything
there are a couple of index registers
there's the stack register the program
counter various other things that you
can't use as easily for generic program
data so I mean ultimately you're sort of
limited to using a few and the compiler
and runtime system typically reserved
also one or two of those for you know a
pointer to global or thread specific
data and and various other things
internally so so ultimately the the
number of registers say on Pentium that
that it can assign values to of your
program are very few okay so now we have
the registers assigned what's next so
the register allocation having been
completed there are a few more RTL
passes to perform some some very
low-level optimizations that are mainly
architecture specific and then the
specific description of the machine that
GCC has for the architecture family for
the processor family and for the
specific chip that you're compiling code
for the description of this machine that
GCC has is used to match this RTL code
against ways of implementing it in the
actual assembly code so the RTL has some
way of representing a you know the
addition of two 32-bit integers let's
say and whenever the whenever that
particular pattern is seen when you're
adding two 32-bit integers whether it be
a register in memory or memory register
or various other memory you know an
offset from memory and a register all
the different addressing modes that are
possible that has matched the RTL
the RTL that that expresses that is
matched and an equivalent assembly
language line or or group of assembly
language instructions is then produced
in the output stream so this is this
this template matching is is performed
by as I said the description of the
specific machine and this machine
description file one which exists for
every back-end available in GCC drives
this this template matching so it can
specifically tell GCC the main GCC
driver okay so this description of the
machine that GCC has for every
architecture for every processor family
and even for specific chips then allows
you to match or allows GCC to match the
specific RTL that it has at this level
with specific assembly instructions that
it knows will will implement it so the
RTL templates look something like you
know set some value that is a register
to some other value which is immediate
and then an immediate constant is quite
cool it's quite modular apparently I
mean you have it's if you're speaking of
this machine description file so is it
it sounds like there is actually one
file for each kind of processor and all
the specifics of the professor processor
are basically in this description file I
mean that's amazing that's that's mostly
true so so with with with certain
caveats but but yes the machine
description file does include a very
large amount of information and codes a
very large amount of information about
what's available in the processor and
what sort of code can be generated
however have some sort of regular
expression or something like that to
describe what sort of RTL you want to
transform into what kind of assembly
output that's true so so basically what
you end up seeing is a number of
different pattern matching groups that
basically say if if the RTL looks
something like this matching on the
different types of the operands and by
types here I basically mean the
addressing mode whether it's an integer
constant versus a register versus a
memory reference
you know and there are various other
details but that sort of thing when
you're doing a simple assignment let's
say from memory into a register in RTL
then the operands can be matched a
certain way to the set instruction the
assigned instruction and then particular
you know a particular assembly language
sequence can be output not everything is
completely encoded in machine
description file because the machine
description file can is actually very
flexible and can rely on external si
functions that you provide in additional
source files so so for example for a a
complicated processor family like the
Intel 32 bit there are actually many
different files that go into into
producing this there's a header file you
know C dot H file that that gives GCC
some idea of what the different
registers available are that gives it
some idea of what different addressing
modes are available and some other
things the machine description file
takes care of a lot of the simple work
of producing assembly code for the
32-bit Intel platform based on certain
RTL template patterns but then anything
more complicated can be an arbitrary C
function can be called reduce assembly
for that so I mean it's basically a very
flexible format where if you want to
escape from the machine description file
format you can call an arbitrary C
function to to match a template or if a
certain template has been matched to to
output the code for it so it is it is
pretty flexible that means that for
something that for a family that has
lots of different chips available that
it wants to support the the specifics of
each then for like like the Intel family
then you can actually get very specific
in the back end and produce a very
efficient code for that specific chip
what about multiprocessor environment or
multi-core and environments that are
common now does the back and to specific
work for optimization for them that's a
good question I I don't believe it does
at this time it produces mainly if
you're talking about a superscalar
architecture where that doesn't have to
pack a large instruction word of of
different parallel instructions to
it's it's not really doing anything of
that of that sort for for masais SNP
Intel again right now it does use
certain I mean basically it will produce
assembly that they have found to be
efficient and so if if they they might
have modified the output assembly of GCC
to do things that are more efficient on
dual-core machines but but I'm not I'm
not familiar with any of the specifics
of that yeah but in the case of a
machine where it's not a very long
instruction word of parallel operations
where the hardware largely takes care of
all of this itself the compiler doesn't
have to do as much if you're talking
about a VL iw machine or something then
then the compiler has to actually
support a lot more in the back end to
advertise what sort of parallelism is
available for the hardware to perform
okay so now we've reached the stage
where actually assembly output is
produced and that is I think basically
the end of the processing that the
compiler per se does that's correct so
the the compiler itself basically it
doesn't do the assembly work itself it
just produces something that can then be
fed into a common assembler for whatever
architecture you have and then further
from there into a linker to produce a a
final binary which you can run but the
the work of producing a architecture
specific program that is equivalent to
the original source program has been
done at this point so basically yes the
compilers work has been done at this
point in GCC it takes that a little bit
step further it all it takes that
several steps further but this sounds
like use somewhat in favor of GCC I i've
been using GCC for many many years and
i'm sure many of your listeners have and
it's it's a very useful tool of one of
its benefits is that it well I mean it
doesn't necessarily it's not alone in
having this benefit certainly other
other tools do this as well but it
doesn't only produce the assembly code
it also provides a driver program that
that wraps the compiler and not only
runs the compiler on your source code
but
also runs the assembler with the correct
arguments runs the linker with the
correct arguments and generally these
are the new assembler in the new linker
but they don't have to be if you're
running on a non new Linux platform for
example but the driver program can then
run these run the compiler on your
source program run the assembler run the
linker everything's taken care of for
you automatically so in fact when I or
you or any of your listeners run GCC at
the command line on their HelloWorld
program it takes care of a lot of this
work for you and you don't ever have to
worry about how to link it proprietary
to to work and so forth on your platform
everything like that is basically taken
care of by its driver program but the
compiler itself for C or C++ or Java or
whatever is is basically done at the
point when it produces an assembly code
okay now let's assume that we are some
of our listeners have become curious and
want to take a closer look at the
internals of GCC what would be some
pointers to actually let's say someone
downloads the source code the entire
source code of GCC over the URL that'll
be the show notes and then also take a
look at some interesting parts of the
source code could you give some pointers
that sort of our key and interesting to
understand what's going on okay would
you like me to navigate the source code
basically hear over the radio sort of
yeah okay so so if you're if you're in
the top level of the of the source tree
you'll actually notice a number of
different directories that that have to
do with various parts of the the entire
platform some of which we haven't talked
about today the most important one is
the GCC directory so you're inside of
the GCC top-level directory and then if
you look at the GCC directory inside of
that you'll find all of the compiler
sources basically all the front ends are
in there all of the the middle end
passes that we talked about today are
there the back ends are all in there
everything else ok so maybe I'll return
to this but but that's that's basically
where everything we've talked about is
there's the Lib standard C++ that's Li
BST DC plus plus v3 directory and that's
the standard C++ library all of the STL
everything else that's implemented as
part of the GCC project but this isn't
part of the
Tyler this is the support the runtime
support library all of the headers all
of the files that are associated the
source files that are associated with
the C++ standard library
there's Lib Java Li BJ a VA which is the
standard Java Runtime that's that's
available for for a new Java compiled
programs and this includes the entire
class library or most of the class
library functionality a lot of the
runtime the dynamic class loading
capabilities which sound sort of weird I
mean having Java code compiled to
natives something that Java developers
really needs to get used to but we'd
like to say some words about why it is
necessary to have separate separate
implementation of the standard Java
library okay so so I mean Java's use
Java folks you aren't just not used to
having their code compiled to native so
it's so this is basically what I'm
talking about here is ahead of time
compilation when you use renews Java
compiler you can you can instruct it to
produce you the usual class file output
you can have it produce a dot class file
just like Java C or jikes would or or
you know Eclipse or any number of things
or you can instruct it to produce object
code you can you know instruct it to
compile it just like it would see or C++
there there are some advantages to that
the advantages are not as many as they
used to be because now there are
sophisticated just-in-time compilers
that can actually do a bit more because
they have a lot of profiling data about
the program as it actually runs the
classes the Java classes and can also
optimize dynamically loaded classes and
various other things but ahead of time
compilation with new Java is very useful
in my work for embedded systems in
particular where you don't have the the
ability because you don't have the
memory or you don't have the resources
you know the power to run a full JVM
with a sophisticated just-in-time
compiler but you don't need the extra
flexibility because of the application
you're working on of having dynamic
class loaded files that are heavily
performing and so basically if you're
talking about a small embedded computer
with very little memory
that that might only run a minimal Linux
kernel if any at all you don't want to
just upload dot class files to it and
then require a large JVM to support
which may not even be available for the
platform for many it's not so ahead of
time compilation into something that's
equivalent to C or C++ code that has
been compiled is then very useful for
these kinds of machines I can be useful
in other in other places as well GCC
does include a lot of optimizations and
can do a tremendous amount before run
time you don't have to pay the overhead
of actually compiling at runtime as you
do with just-in-time compilers and so
for many programs gcj compiled Java
programs can perform very well compared
to other approaches sophisticated JVMs
with with highly optimizing just-in-time
compilers in them mm-hmm so it's it's
not necessarily a bad thing to ahead of
Ted of time compile everything ahead of
time I'm sorry that's it's it's not
necessarily a bad thing to compile
everything ahead of time as opposed to
producing a dot class file but there are
advantages and disadvantages the
disadvantages of course are that it's no
longer portable you can't distribute
your dot class file to everybody on
every hardware architecture and expect
it to work so we go back to this
directory structure of what let's look
at two or three interesting files
what would you say our key actually
source files of the GCC that give an
idea of what's actually going on people
should look at every one to get an idea
ok well I'll probably have to give
slightly more than three that's ok maybe
30 I can I can give a few pointers if
you're opening up the GCC source tree
and you're interested in looking at a
few files in the compiler that are most
interesting you can go inside the GCC
directory and then inside the config
directory and you'll find a directory
for every back-end that's available
every hardware architecture right so I
386 let's pick on because we've been
picking on it so far today you can go
into the i386 directory and then you'll
find an i3
six dot MD file and that's the machine
description file that I mentioned before
and inside of there you'll find a lot of
RTL templates they're the things that
look like Lisp symbolic expressions if
you're familiar with them you'll find a
lot of those that match standard
operations that GCC needs to perform
with with The Associated RTL and with
The Associated assembly instructions so
that's one place that's sort of
interesting to look to to see that
instruction selection phase so that's at
the end it's starting back at the
top-level directory if you go into the
GCC source directory and then look at
the passes C file you'll see what's what
what drives the middle end this is the
pass manager that I mentioned before
that it orders all of the different
optimization passes not only on the tree
representation but also on the RTL
representation so that's where the list
of all the optimizations is basically is
one call per optimization for all these
dozens of passes that actually take
place and that's right that's right and
if you have you look for the C macro
next underscore pass all uppercase if
I'm trying to remember what the source
file looks like here without lo being
able to look at it you'll find all of
the different passes ordered there so if
you're interested in what passes are
performed and what orders that's a good
place to look most of those passes have
similarly named source files that are
available in that same directory so then
if you're interested in say dead code
elimination as I mentioned before which
is the DCE optimization then you can
look at the in the same directory you
can look at the tree - SSA - d c-- e dot
c file and that's that's the the the
dead code elimination pass for GCC and
if you look through that source code
you'll that source file you'll see
exactly how dead code elimination is
done on the tree representation inside
of GCC so there there are no secrets
here it's an open source project and you
can and you can take a look at
everything and everything's accessible
so that's the middle end if you're
interested in the front ends I would i
would
and for Java its most easily accessible
I suppose and just because of the way
that the front end is is structured and
the fact that many people know Java I
don't know your listener pace I suppose
but Java is usually a simpler language
to look at then than C++ because of the
additional features that C++ has that
makes language implementations a little
bit more difficult you're here
well sometimes writing in C++ can be
more difficult but at least language
implement implementers have a larger job
I was just joking C++ great there's good
reason so you super fastest yeah Java is
simpler obviously yeah it just as an
aside I am one of those rare programming
language people that don't have
necessarily a favorite language i i i
don't favor java over c++ over parole
over Oh camel over Haskell over Python
or anything else I enjoy all these
languages for 4 different projects and
when when a particular project that I'm
attacking doesn't fit naturally into a
language I tend to pick another one or
if there are many different ones that
are possible I choose them by random
lots because it's it's it's interesting
to maintain a good skill set across many
different languages and to expose
yourself to a lot of different things
but I don't I don't really have a
favorite language I enjoy implementing
languages I like writing programs in
various different languages and and I I
guess I'm more interested in comparing
languages then then then evangelizing
yeah
however ok so at least at least in this
case I can say that Java is easier to
implement in some ways certainly at the
language level and and so anyway so
inside of the GCC directory inside of
the Java subdirectory you can look at
parse dot Y and this is a a C like file
even despite the dot Y extension
it's a yak grama problem it's a yes it's
a a well it's a bison grammar which is
largely compatible back with with yak
which it's few tens of thousands of
lines long I think it contains a lot of
support functions
because it contains a lot of support
functions beyond the actual grammar but
this is where the entire Java grammar
lives and how it parses those things and
how it generates this this initial tree
structure before it has to go through
and semantically analyze it and complete
it that that's an excellent place to
start looking at at the java front-end
to figure out exactly how it operates on
different source level constructs and
then from there you can trace through
how different parts of that front-end
work thank you very much it's been fun
discussing GCC with you
Thank You Arnhem Thank You Morgan
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se dash radio dot net you can also
contact the team at team at SAE - radio
net although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the soft engineering radio website
for details